A Guide to the Papers of John Powell, 1888-1978, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series IV: Eugenics and Racial Integrity
  - B. Correspondence concerning eugenics: John Powell
    - Atha Sorrells v. A. T. Shields, Clerk, Rockbridge County. Petition for Mandamus, 1925, 1 TMs, 3 pp. (Box-folder 39:70)
      The court decides that a marriage license can be issued by A. T. Shields for Atha Sorrells and Robert Painter. Judge [Henry W. Holt] decides that even though he is very supportive of racial integrity legislation, there is a lack of evidence showing her to be Colored. Holt writes that without evidence, mixed couples are free to marry. He states, "We find ourselves where we were in the beginning. Alice herself never got into a deeper tangle."
    - Addresses and newsletters for Anglo-Saxon members, [1925], 1 TM, 14 pp. (Box-folder 39:71)
    - [Verbon] to John Powell, January 17, 1926, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 39:72)
      [Verbon] writes that, "I have interested a number of fellows here at the Y in your work and I believe an Anglo-Saxon Club could be formed. I went by to see Ernest Cox when in Richmond and had a dandy talk with him about his new book. I think Let My People Go is a master piece. I ordered a dozen copies and distributed them among friends, always with the request that they pass it on to their friends."
    - Earnest Sevier Cox to the Honorable J. P. Jones, January 22, 1926, 3 TMs, 8 pp. (Box-folder 39:73)
      Cox writes about the history of the American Colonization Society and encloses the House Joint Resolution "memorializing the Congress of the United States..." to provide for the colonization of persons of African descent, at their own request, in Liberia, or anywhere in Africa. There are also typed notes included with the House Joint Resolution.
    - Ivan E. McDougle to Louise Burleigh Powell, January 24, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:74)
      McDougle writes about his book on racial integrity, "There is no question in my mind that this book will create a stir and shock some people for years to come if they read it."
    - John Ingrame Brookes to W. Clyde Maddox, February 20, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:75)
      Brookes requests that Powell visit Charlotte County, Virginia in order to organize an Anglo-Saxon Club.
    - Henley Guy to Senator, February 28, 1926, TLS, 2 pp (Box-folder 39:76)
      Guy sends a copy of his letter pleading for the passage of the Massenburg bill which forbids the mixing of the races. He writes, "...Some say it is a disgrace to the state of Virginia to pass a law to keep white people from going to colored entertainments but it will be a further disgrace if such a law is defeated in the Virginia legislature, thereby giving the cue to Du Bois and his white niggers to resume their campaign for social equality in Virginia and if in Virginia, the entire South, and if the South, the entire United States will be involved." Guy also mentions "the dangerous precedent that the Hampton Institute is setting by allowing the mixing of the races."
    - Arthur Gray to John Powell, March 2, 1926, 2 TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 39:77)
      Gray writes an editorial to The Richmond Times-Dispatch defending the "Bear Mountain Mission." He requests that his name be kept anonymous and wants Powell to send in the editorial for him. Included is a note from Powell to the editor of the newspaper, "I received to day the following statement, sent me by one in whom I have every confidence, who wished that his name be withheld."
    - John Powell to Mrs. B. B. Munford, March 5, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:78)
      Powell threatens opponents of the Massenburg bill which requires all segregated seating at public assemblies. Powell writes, "In all seriousness, I warn you that the defeat of this bill may bring tragedy and horror upon the oldest English-speaking community in America." He adds that others support this view, such as Judge Spratley, who pleaded for it with "a broken voice and tearful eyes." He warns that he "does not envy the opponents of this bill the responsibility they are unnecessarily and gratuitously assuming." He also writes that this letter "was inspired by a sincere desire to spare you bitter regret."
    - Dr. G. Jarvis Bowens to John Powell, March 6, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:79)
      Bowens requests a copy of Mongrels in Virginia by John Powell.
    - John Powell to the Editor, The Baltimore Evening Sun, March 6, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:80)
      Powell defends an "attack" that was made on him for his legislation that proposes the raising of taxes on cosmetics and a racial integrity law. The criticism is made by Mr. Mencken from the The Baltimore Evening Sun.
    - Reid Williams to Louise Burleigh Powell, March 7, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:81)
      Williams is interested and anxious to help, but since he is so far away he needs to be kept informed of what they want him to do.
    - John Powell to the Editor, The Boston Evening Transcript, March 8, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:82)
      Powell thanks the newspaper for their appreciative comment during a time of criticism on his racial legislation before the Virginia General Assembly. Powell claims that Negroes were registering as Indians creating a "path from black to white." He explains that the pattern went from "Indianoid negro to Negroid Indian, Negroid Indian to plain Indian, plain Indian to Indianoid white, whose marriage to a white person established his position in the white class."
    - B.F. Averill to John Powell, March 8, 1926, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:83)
      Averill writes in support of colonization and has many ideas about its financing. He names several people who he thinks would be helpful such as, H.S. Firestone, who could create jobs in Liberia by investing $100,000 for rubber production. He also discusses Marcus Garvey, "a man of remarkable influence". He also writes that, "given a good start off and the colored race will follow their leaders-like sheep through a broken fence."
    - Henley Guy to John Powell, March 9, 1926, ALS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:84)
      Guy writes about the Massenburg bill, "Our Separation Bill will come out victorious...It was suggested that each one of us write a letter to Senator Holt regarding the Massenburg Bill...I thought it a good plan to mail one to each Senator as well as our two local representatives in the House, Mr. Massenburg and Mr. Mugler...."
    - Louise Burleigh Powell to Judge Bolte, March 18, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:85)
      Louise Powell writes that "Dr. Plecker asked her to answer Judge Bolte's wire asking if a list of prominent people who are negroid has been published." She responds that no such list has been published by Dr.Plecker or Mr. Powell. She also writes that the editor of The Richmond News-Leader is concerned that many aristocrats will be classified as "colored" if the new legislation is passed. She explains that the bill is designed to exclude only the Indians who have mixed with Negroes.
    - Dr. A. E. Soliman to John Powell, March 19, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:86)
      Soliman writes that he notices that Powell is for repatriation and offers his volume of work for Powell to review. Soliman is coming to meet with President Coolidge but first wants to find out the public opinion on the subject.
    - B. F. Averill to Louise Burleigh Powell, March 25, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:87)
      Averill thanks her for the enclosures and regrets that he can't do much work on establishing a post. He writes, "You see, I have passed 70 birthdays and that is telling enough of the story why not."
    - Louise Burleigh Powell to John Powell, March 25, 1926, TLS, 5 pp. (Box-folder 39:88)
      Louise Powell reviews the book, Free Negro Heads of Families in 1830. She writes that the book is confusing and depicts the legislation against miscegenation as "a desire to reduce the free negroes to slavery- nothing else." She also writes that Dr. Plecker is now accepting the 1924 law with its compromises but is still negative about the possibility of passing better legislation. She also writes "[Plecker] said that the Massenburg bill became a law automatically without the Governor's signature."
    - Caleb G. Robinson to John Powell, March 26, 1926, ALS, 17 pp. (Box-folder 39:89)
      Robinson introduces himself as a black professor, president of the Institution of Learning at Claremont, Virginia and secret supporter of Marcus Garvey's Back to Africa and the United Negro Improvement Association (U.N.I.A.) The letter tells the history of the Institute and the plans to make it the Back to Africa southern headquarters. There is a debt of $60,000 on the mortgage that needs to be paid by April 9th. They need a loan until the U.N.I.A. has time to come up with the funds. He is heartbroken to lose the school and pleads with Powell for a loan in utmost secrecy.
    - [Unidentified] to John Powell, March 1926, ALS, 4 pp. (Box-folder 39:90)
      The correspondent writes, "In all your propaganda regarding racial relation, it appear [sic] that you are aiming to vindicate the white men. In the days of slavery in America, white men forced negro women to bed with them and if they resisted they were flogged or sold. The same rule is in force today, only in a different way." The correspondent explains that employers put pressure on "a negro girl or woman" to sleep with them or they will lose their jobs. The point is also made that "white men started this mixed color, and they are try [sic] to keep at it by using racial integrity as a veil to protect them, and at the same time defile our race...It isn't fair." There is a note in pencil on the envelope, "This needs no answer!-but I wish it could have one."
    - Louise Burleigh Powell to John Powell, March 30, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:91)
      Louise Powell questions how to respond to Caleb G. Robinson's letter in which Robinson requests Powell's help with a loan for the Institute of Learning. She writes, "He seemed so very secret about it all that I wondered whether he was quite sane! However, I imagine he is, and I hope that he and his Garveyites will get their school." She also writes, "The Garvey paper carried a glowing account of Garvey's triumph over Sherrill..." She also mentions that she received a book from Dr. Soliman of Hollywood, California, The Past, Present and Future of the Negro.
    - S. J. Holmes to John Powell, April 2, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:92)
      Holmes writes that he is glad to call a meeting of their Eugenics Section at the Commonwealth Club.
    - Louise Burleigh Powell to John Powell, April 8, 1926, TLS, 5 pp. and enclosure. (Box-folder 39:93)
      Louise Powell writes that she is working hard on Jurgen and finds it depressing. She sends him a news clipping of an editorial titled, Negro Segregation North. It concerns legislation in Indianapolis and remarks that the legislation in the North would be similar to that in the South if they had as many Negroes as in the South.
    - A.H. Shannon to John Powell, May 29, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:94)
      Shannon asks Powell, Cox and Plecker for a statement of their publications. He also sends a copy of a pamphlet that he has published and is preparing a list of valuable publications dealing with the mixture of the races.
    - V. S. McClatchy to John Powell, June 24, 1926, 2 TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:95)
      McClatchy sends Powell a copy of the Commonwealth Club discussion on eugenics with Professor Holmes, Chairman of the Eugenics Section, in which Holmes refers to Powell for further information. McClatchy also writes to Mrs. Victor Brenner, Secretary of the publishing company which issues the Survey of New York, and suggests that she issue a survey on the mongrelization of the white race. He writes that she is currently investigating the subject of Mexican immigration.
    - Bettina [Powell] to John Powell, August 6, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:96)
      Bettina hopes that Powells' talks will be successful and that the "darkies will soon be all carted off to Liberia."
    - John Powell to Mr. Smith, November 25, 1926, TLS, 4 pp. Draft. (Box-folder 39:97)
      Powell writes that he saw an announcement in the paper for Pamunkey Reservation inhabitants to sell "Indian handicraft." Powell advises Smith that there are no Indians in this location. He informs Smith that he is copying this letter to Dr. Plecker in the hopes that Plecker will show Smith the records and explain "the difficulties- I should say horrors- which have sprung from this Indian claim."
    - Mabel Tuttle to John Powell, December 16, 1926, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 39:98)
      Tuttle writes, "I must hear.. and know what you mean to do about the negro question."
    - Frank R. Hopkins to John Powell, March 19, 1927, TLS, 7 pp. (Box-folder 39:99)
      Hopkins writes that, "Anti-Southern editorials in The Rochester Democrat Chronicle have stimulated me to pass my opinion on to you."
    - Lothrop Stoddard to John Powell, April 23, 1927, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:100)
      Stoddard writes, "I am sending an advance copy of my new book, Re-Forging America. I feel you will be especially interested in the chapters on the race question. When you have read the book, I would esteem it a great favor if you would write me your opinion of it."
    - Sylvia F. Metcalf to John Powell, April 29, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:101)
      Metcalf forwards an article on "The Problem" that she has written. She explains that it is similar to Cox's opinions. She also writes that New Orleans is not interested in the subject and that "Nobody cares! What a tragedy it all is."
    - Mary B. Baughman, M.D. to John Powell, August 20, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:102)
      Baughman suggests combining the members pledged to the Racial Integrity Association with the State Eugenics Society. He also mentions Leon F. Whitney and meeting schedules.
    - James C. Davis to John Powell, August 22, 1927, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:103)
      Davis writes that the racial integrity bill passes in Atlanta.
    - E. C. Folkes to John Powell, August 25, 1927, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:104)
      Folkes writes, "I was asked what does Richmond need and I said...more men like John Powell who has dreamed a dream of saving our race and all over our land is preaching a doctrine of racial integrity."
    - N.E. Clement to the Honorable Letcher A. Bryant, August 27, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:105)
      Clement introduces Judge Bryant to Powell.
    - Harry C. Fickler to [John Powell], August 27, 1927, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:106)
      Fickler writes, "It will be both a surprise and a disappointment if I do not support any amendment to the racial integrity statute which you may propose..."
    - George Mallison to John Powell, October 7, 1927, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:107)
      Mallison asks, "Can you read my manuscript for errors and suggestions. I gave it to Mr. Copeland at Dr. Plecker's suggestion but it was too large for him to undertake. Christopher Publishing House and Harpers are not interested in considering it or proofing it... I got an amusing letter (pompous) from one Mr.Woodson, author of A Century of Negro Migration..."
    - Edward Meeks to John Powell, October 8, 1927, TLS 1p. (Box-folder 39:108)
      Meeks prepares for his court cases, Commonwealth vs. Mary Hall and Mott H. Wood by requesting help from the Governor of Virginia and information from Dr. Plecker. He emphasizes that a case cannot be won without evidence.
    - Dr. A. E. Soliman to John Powell, December 27, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:109)
      Soliman wishes a Merry Christmas to Powell and the club members. He writes that he is now the author of The Past, Present, Future of the Negro.
    - Claude A. Swanson to John Powell, January 11, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:110)
      Swanson writes that he needs Powell to be more specific about what he wants the government to do. Swanson will talk with Ambassador Houghton if Powell will write his proposed plans.
    - Claude F. Swanson to John Powell, January 16, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:111)
      Swanson writes that he would be glad to set up a meeting with Powell.
    - W. E. Sandidge to John Powell, January 18, 1928, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:112)
      Sandidge offers suggestions for the proposed amendment to the racial integrity law. The Virginia law provides that a license can be withheld when there is doubt about whether the applicant is Colored. Sandidge proposes that the law also needs to ensure that a white person does not falsely claim to be Colored in order to intermarry. He also has concerns that the clerk does not have the authority for determining an individual's racial status.
    - John Powell to Judge Gordon. February 7, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:113)
      Powell writes that he is sending White America, an Anglo-Saxon pamphlet, and The Breach in the Dyke. He also writes that two bills were introduced into the House by James H. Price and passed. He states, "the Bill defining colored persons we got through the Senate Courts of Justice Committee after a battle royal with the Redskins, who say they will all tie millstones round their necks and jump into the Pamunkey river if they are classed as colored and yet demand that as much as seventy-five percent negro blood be permitted in the Indian class."
    - Louise Powell to John Powell, February 13, 1928, 1 telegram. (Box-folder 39:114)
      Louise Powell writes that Bill No.25 was enacted and Bill No. 2 was defeated 26-13. She writes that there was a fight over the Indians on the floor with Senators Wickham and Haddon against Senator Booker. She mentions that, "Senators Norris and Warren were lobbying of Blackwell [and] Ryland had more effect than speeches. Some things were fun." She describes Plecker as "disappointed but not downcast."
    - Dorothy Kaltenbach to John Powell, February 14, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:115)
      Kaltenbach, Secretary to Mr. McClatchy writes, "Mr. McClatchy has become interested in the radical situation in this country since last seeing you. The radicals, as you no doubt know, are encouraging the negroes to agitate for racial equality."
    - G. E. Inman to John Powell, February 15, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:116)
      Inman asks Powell to speak at a meeting in Oklahoma.
    - Annabel Buchanan to John Powell, February 17, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:117)
      Buchanan writes, in a postscript, "I am distressed over the failure of that bill to pass the Senate- glad to see that Papa was among those who voted for it..."
    - Annabel Buchanan to John Powell, March 23, 1929, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 39:118)
      Buchanan wants to invite the Hampton Choir to sing at the concert so she asks Powell for his advice. She writes, "If it were simply a question of prejudice to negro singers, I wouldn't consider that at all- we'd owe it to our negro musicians to pay some attention to what they are doing, especially when they're doing considerably better choral work than anybody else in Virginia. If negroes can do work like that, with the choral work we're trying to put over in the state and the interest we are trying to arouse, that should be an inspiration to the white people."
    - Earnest Sevier Cox to Mrs. Betty Powell Brockenbrough, April 15, 1929, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:119)
      Cox writes her a thank you note for her card of sympathy for him when he lost the companionship of his dog.
    - James S. Easley to John Powell, February 7, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:120)
      Easley writes that their bill had a second reading yesterday but was passed by because Hill Montague was not well and did not want to have a contest. Easley states that a substitute bill was ordered printed, but Easley did not see it. He writes, "I understand that it is to amend the language on our bill so as to let in the Chickahominy tribe, and we are going to fight that to the bitter end..."
    - A. M. Finch to John Powell, February 27, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:121)
      Finch has studied "Virginia's Legislative Enactments on the Racial Problem since the Civil War" in graduate school and asks for Powell's help.
    - Lamar Stringfield to John Powell, May 19, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:122)
      Stringfield writes mostly about music for the flute and folk song collections but he mentions this incident, "Harry Rohm, my jew from Richmond that hit me with his car, rather than pay the full amount of the settlement of the case, made a good arrangement of getting out of paying the amount by getting murdered last Monday night. I do not know who did it, but I am sure if it had been me, I would have made it a tormenting job, rather than a complete and sudden departure from this world."
    - George Taylor Ross to John Powell, August 27, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:123)
      Ross introduces Mr. Leif Egeland who is investigating Negro conditions for the Rhodes Foundation. He writes, "I think that your discussions on the negro question would be mutually profitable and interesting."
    - F. E. Bushey to the Registrar of Vital Statistics, October 31, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:124)
      Bushey requests the address of the Anglo Saxon Club in Richmond, Virginia.
    - Publishers of Sinister Shadows to John Powell, November 5, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 39:125)
      The publishers request information on the Anglo-Saxon Club Richmond. They write, "You may be familiar with our activities. We are publishers of Sinister Shadows which is an American book that you will endorse when you read about the stand it takes against mixed marriages. We are inclosing [sic] a pamphlet, The Brass Weather cock and also one entitled At the Cross Road."
    - E. C. Folkes to John Powell, March 24, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 40:1)
      Folkes writes, "...I said you were truly great because you are a great dreamer. That in your soul was the dream of the purity of the races being maintained God like and beautiful, like God himself directed and punished when Israel dared to disobey..."
    - W. Clyde Maddox to John Powell, May 3, 1931, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 40:2)
      Maddox writes that he would like Powell to hear his sister's maid play her instrument. He also writes, "Had a long talk with Hobart Hall... conversation harked back to the days when we were cyclopes, dragons and what-nots." He said that while his KKK experience had been costly in loss of patronage, he had been more than repaid by his association with some of us, you of course included. "Do you ever recall the tense situations we had to face and the momentous [ ] decisions we had to make in 1921?"
    - Edmund Eitel to John Powell, June 25, 1931, 1TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 40:3)
      Eitel writes to Powell about a square dance they are holding at the Buffalo Mineral Springs Hotel. One of the tunes starts, Yonder, nigger 'cross the field....
    - A. D. Latane to the Honorable W. A. Plecker, July 20, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 40:4)
      Latane, Clerk, Circuit Court of Essex County writes that he received Plecker's letter about the families in Essex and surrounding counties who claim to have Indian blood and who have tried to effect a tribe organization. He writes that he can take the matter up with the local authorities and is willing to help.
    - A. H. Shannon to [John Powell], November 9, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 40:5)
      Shannon writes about the astounding progress of amalgamation since 1870. He also mentions a book dealing primarily with racial intermixture between the Negro and the Caucasian, called The Negro in Washington: A Study in Race Amalgamation.
    - Basset Hough to John Powell, November 30, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 40:6)